<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<!-- insert xhtml content here -->

<h3>Примечания для реализаторов</h3>
<p>
A referenced DICOM SOP instance could be: 
<ul>
<li>A single- or multi-frame, still or video image captured by a variety of imaging modalities, such as X-ray, MR, and ultrasound;</li>
<li>A set of various presentation parameters, including annotation and markup;</li>
<li>A set of measurements or a report, including radiation dose report and CAD analysis;</li>
<li>An encapsulated PDF or CDA document;</li>
<li>A list of instances, such as key “of interest” images, or instances to be “deleted”; or </li>
<li>Other DICOM content. </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
UID values follow the FHIR convention of expressing UIDs as URNs. For example, the DICOM Study Instance UID 
of <code>1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910</code> is expressed as <code>“urn:oid:1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910”</code>. 
</p>
<p>  
The ImagingManifest.study.endpoint elements and ImagingManifest.study.series.endpoint elements indicate network 
services that can be used to access the studies, series, or instances; for example, a DICOM WADO-RS server. An 
ImagingManifest.study.series.endpoint of a particular Endpoint.connectionType provides that service for that 
series, and all contained instances. An ImagingManifest.study.endpoint of a particularconnection type provides 
that service for all series in that study that do not have a specified Endpoint of that type, and their 
contained instances. That is, an ImagingManifest.study.series.endpoint overrides a ImagingManifest.study.endpoint 
of the same connection type. (Since each study, or individual series of a study can be stored on different imaging 
archive servers, per-series endpoints are required. For the identified services and use cases, all instances within 
a series would be stored together, and thus instance-level endpoints are not defined.)
</p>
<p>
Different Endpoint connection types may have different capabilities, protocols or requirements; and the specified 
Endpoint.url may require manipulation. For the details on use of imaging-related Endpoint connection types, 
See below for details.
</p>
<a name="endpoint"> </a>
<h4>WADO-RS</h4>
<p>
An <code>Endpoint.connectionType</code> of code <code>dicom-wado-rsi</code>, system <code>http://hl7.org/fhir/endpoint-connection-type</code>, 
identifies a DICOM WADO-RS service. The <code>Endpoint.address</code> identifies the HTTP(S) service base url. 
That is, only the scheme, authority and path are included. Sub-services, such as study, shall not be specified. 
The path shall not contain a trailing slash.
</p>
<p>
The DICOM WADO-RS (Web Access to DICOM Objects, RESTful mode) service uses a RESTful approach to instance retrieval.
This service allows for retrieval of native DICOM SOP instances, or instances “rendered” into other formats, including
JPEG and MPEG. The media type of a response is specified by the request Accept header (preferred); or, by the accept
query parameters. Supported media types depend on the  capabilities of the WADO-RS server and the classification of the instance 
as “single frame,” “multi-frame,” “video,” “text,” or “other.” The WADO-RS service also allows retrieval of study
or series level information.
</p>
<p>
The path to retrieve a DICOM instance is constructed by appending the appropriate sub-resource paths to the <code>Endpoint.address</code> value.
</p>
<p>
For example, a native DICOM PS3.10 instance file can be retrieved (if consistent with the Accept header) by
performing a GET on a URL constructed from a <code>Endpoint.address</code> of <code>“https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs”</code>, the
study.uid value
of <code>“urn:oid:1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910”</code>, study.series.uid value
of <code>“urn:oid:1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789”</code>, and study.series.instance.uid value
of <code>“urn:oid:1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2”</code>:
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs/studies/1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910/series/1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789/instances/1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2

</pre>
<p>
Query parameters on the "rendered" sub-resource can control other aspects of the rendering including: the rendered dimensions, the
quality (compression ratio), the region of interest to render, the brightness/contrast (window center/width)
adjustments, and whether to “burn” patient or study demographics into the rendered result. Specific frames
of a multi-frame instance may be retrieved using the frames sub-resource.
</p>
<p>
For example, provided the Accept header indicates a preference for image/jpeg, the example above can be
extended with parameters that cause a JPEG thumbnail (100 columns by 100 rows) of a region extending from
the top-left corner of the original image, across 1000 and down 3000 pixels, to be retrieved (additional
sub-resource and parameters emphasized):
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-rs/studies/1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910/series/1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789/instances/1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2<b>/rendered?viewport=100,100,0,0,1000,3000</b>

</pre>
<p>
For further details on DICOM WADO-RS capabilities including additional rendering parameters,
see <a href="http://dicom.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/chtml/part18/PS3.18.html">DICOM PS 3.18</a>.
</p>
<h4>WADO-URI</h4>
<p>An Endpoint.connectionType of code <code>dicom-wado-uri</code>, system <code>http://hl7.org/fhir/endpoint-connection-type</code>, 
identifies a DICOM WADO-URI service. The Endpoint.address identifies the HTTP(S) service base url. 
That is, only the scheme, authority and path are included. Neither a quetstion mark (?) nor any query parameters shall be included.
</p>
<p>
The DICOM WADO-URI (Web Access to DICOM Objects, URI mode) service uses HTTP query parameter syntax. This service allows
for retrieval of native DICOM instances, or instances “rendered” into other formats, including JPEG and MPEG. The media
type of a response is specified by the request Accept header (preferred); or, by the contentType query parameter.
Supported media types depend on the classification of the instance as “single frame,” “multi-frame,” “video,” “text,” or “other.”
</p>
<p>
The query to retrieve a DICOM instance is constructed by appending the appropriate query parameters to the <code>Endpoint.address.url</code>.
</p>
<p>
For example, a native DICOM PS3.10 instance file can be retrieved (if consistent with the Accept header) by performing
a GET on a URL constructed from a <code>Endpoint.address.url</code> of <code>“https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-uri”</code>, the study.uid value
of <code>“urn:oid:1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910”</code>, study.series.uid value
of <code>“urn:oid:1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789”</code>, and study.series.instance.uid value
of <code>“urn:oid:1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2”</code>:
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-uri?requestType=WADO&amp;studyUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910&amp;seriesUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789&amp;objectUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2

</pre>

<p>
Additional query parameters can control other aspects of the rendering including rendered dimensions, quality (compression
ratio), the region of interest within the image to render, brightness/contrast (window center/width) adjustments, whether
to “burn” patient or study demographics into the rendered result, and which frame of a multi-frame instance to retrieve.
</p>
<p>
For example, provided the Accept header indicates a preference for image/jpeg, the example above can be extended with
parameters that cause a JPEG thumbnail (100 columns by 100 rows) of the left half of the image to be retrieved (additional
parameters emphasized):
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/wado-uri?requestType=WADO&amp;studyUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910&amp;seriesUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.789001276.14556172.67789&amp;objectUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.2678810.87991027.899772.2&amp;<b>rows=100&amp;columns=100&amp;region=0,0,0.5,1 </b>

</pre>
<p>
For further details on DICOM WADO-URI capabilities including additional rendering parameters,
see <a href="http://dicom.nema.org/medical/dicom/current/output/chtml/part18/PS3.18.html">DICOM PS 3.18</a>.
</p>
<h4>IID</h4>
<p>An Endpoint.connectionType of code <code>ihe-iid</code>, system <code>http://hl7.org/fhir/endpoint-connection-type</code>, identifies an IHE 
<b>Invoke Image Display (IID)</b> service. The <code>Endpoint.address</code> identifies the HTTP(S) service base url. 
That is, only the scheme, authority and path are included. Neither the question mark (“?”) nor any query parameters shall be included.
</p>
<p>
The IHE <b>Invoke Image Display (IID)</b> service provides a standardized mechanism to launch a viewer in a particular study 
context. (IID also supports invoking a particular patient context, but that is not profiled here.) An IID-type Endpoint should 
be used only at the study level. As well as invoking the viewer on a particular study, query parameters can request particular 
viewer capabilities, image quality, and more.
</p>
<p>
To launch a viewer, append the appropriate query parameters to <code>Endpoint.address</code> value.
</p>
<p>
For example, given an <code>Endpoint.address</code> of <code>https://pacs.hospital.org/IHEInvokeImageDisplay</code>, to 
invoke a diagnostic quality viewer on the study with <code>study.uid</code> value of <code>“urn:uri:1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910”</code>, 
the following URL would be constructed:
</p>
<pre>

https://pacs.hospital.org/IHEInvokeImageDisplay?requestType=STUDY&amp;studyUID=1.2.250.1.59.40211.12345678.678910&amp;diagnosticQuality=true

</pre>
<p>
For further details on IHE Invoke Image Display capabilities including additional parameters, see
the <a href="http://www.ihe.net/Technical_Frameworks/#radiology">IHE Technical Frameworks</a>, 
or the introduction on the <a href="http://wiki.ihe.net/index.php/Invoke_Image_Display">IHE IID Profile Wiki</a>.
</p>
<h3>Сценарий использования<!-- Use Case --></h3>
<h4>Доступ к результатам радиологических исследований из ЭМК<!-- EHR access to imaging studies --></h4>
<p>
Эми, семейный врач, обращается к реестру документов предприятия, содержащему результаты радиологических исследований (<a href="http://www.ihe.net">IHE Radiology XDS-I</a>), чтобы найти исследования её пациента Алекса. Её ЭМК-клиент выполняет FHIR-вызов всех доступных объектов <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> для Алекса. В ответ она может получить идентификаторы исследований для каждого исследования, которое было опубликовано в этот реестр. В ответ предоставляется достаточно информации, чтобы получить эскиз через вызов WADO-RS или запустить просмотрщик с помощью вызова профиля <a href="http://www.ihe.net">IHE Radiology - Invoke Image Display (IID)</a>, используя элементы URL, находящиеся в <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a>.
<!-- Amy, a family physician, would like to see a list of available studies for her patient, Alex. Her EHR 
client makes a FHIR call for all <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> objects available for Alex. 
In the response, she is able to see the study date, procedure, modality, and accession number, for each 
study returned. There is enough information provided in the response to obtain a thumbnail via a WADO-RS 
call, or to launch a viewer using an <a href="http://www.ihe.net">IHE Radiology - Invoke Image Display (IID)</a> 
profile call using the url elements found in the <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a>. -->
</p>
<h4>Всеобъемлющий плановый рабочий процесс работы с радиологическими изображениями<!-- Comprehensive Imaging Scheduled Workflow --></h4>
<p>
Джо Энджене жалуется на одышку и нерегулярную боль в груди своему основному лечащему врачу доктору Пату Дауну в местной поликлинике, который заказал для него стресс-эхокардиограмму; этот заказ создаётся в виде FHIR-ресурса <a href="task.html">Task</a> для управления рабочим процессом, со ссылкой на ресурс <a href="procedurerequest.html">ProcedureRequest</a> с деталями запроса. Заказ запланирован, и его исполнение назначенено кардиологу доктору Арту Сканну, также работающему в этой поликлинике.
</p>
<p>
В назначенный по расписанию день обследования Джо прибывает в лабораторию ультразвуковой эхографии для встречи с доктором Сканном и выполнения исследования. Рабочая станция доктора Сканна показывает ежедневный список <a href="task.html">Task</a>, и он переходит по ссылке для открытия заказа на диагностическое исследование (<a href="procedurerequest.html">ProcedureRequest</a>). Он может перейти по ссылкам из ресурса <a href="patient.html">Patient</a> для доступа к электронной истории болезни Джо, но в данном случае нас это не интересует.
<!-- On the scheduled day of the exam, Joe arrives at the echo lab to meet with Dr. Skann and have the study done.  
Dr. Skann’s workstation shows the daily list of <a href="task.html">Task</a>, and he follows the link to retrieve the 
<a href="diagnosticrequest.html">DiagnosticRequest</a>. (He may follow the links through the 
referenced <a href="patient.html">Patient</a> resource to access Joe’s electronic 
medical record, but that is not the concern of this storyboard.)   -->
</p>
<p>
<a href="task.html">Task</a> и <a href="procedurerequest.html">ProcedureRequest</a> были перекодированы в DICOM Modality Worklist Scheduled Procedure Step, а оборудование в лаборатории ультразвуковой эхографии скачало Modality Worklist. Исследование выполнено, и полученные изображения и предварительные измерения специалиста по ультразвуковой эхографии сохранены в локальной системе передачи и архивации изображений поликлиники (PACS). Система создаёт ресурс <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> для каждого проводимого исследования.
<!-- The <a href="task.html">Task</a> and <a href="procedurerequest.html">ProcedureRequest</a> has been transcoded to a DICOM Modality Worklist 
Scheduled Procedure Step, and in the echo lab the equipment has downloaded the Modality Worklist.  The 
study is performed, and the acquired images and sonographer’s preliminary measurements are stored in the 
Local MultiClinic Picture Archiving and Communication System (PACS).  The PACS creates 
an <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> resource for each study it manages. -->
</p>
<p>
Доктор Сканн интерпретирует результаты исследования на рабочей станции системы PACS и выбирает два ключевых кадра изображения для включения в диагностический отчёт; эта выборка сохраняется в системе PACS в виде DICOM-выборки ключевых объектов под заголовком "Для приложения к отчёту", и PACS делает её доступной (перекодирует её) в виде FHIR-ресурса <a href="imagingmanifest.html">ImagingManifest</a>. Доктор Сканн диктует отчёт, используя программу написания отчётов структурированного ввода данных, включая рекомендацию катетеризации полостей сердца, и подписывает его. Программа написания отчётов оформляет документ в виде <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=7">CDA</a>-документа, извлекает ресурс <a href="imagingmanifest.html">ImagingManifest</a> и вставляет отмеченные ключевые изображения в этот отчёт.
<!-- Dr. Skann interprets the study on a PACS workstation, and he selects two key image frames to be included 
in the diagnostic report; this selection is stored back to the PACS as a DICOM Key Object Selection with 
the title "For Report Attachment", and the PACS makes it available (transcodes it) as a 
FHIR <a href="imagingmanifest.html">ImagingManifest</a> resource.  Dr. Skann dictates the 
report using a structured data entry report writing program, including a recommendation for a cardiac 
catheterization procedure, and signs it.  The report writing program formats the report 
as a <a href="http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=7">CDA</a> document, 
retrieves the <a href="imagingmanifest.html">ImagingManifest</a> resource, and inserts the 
referenced key images into the report. -->
</p>
<p>
Доктор Даун снова встречается с Джо, и они просматривают результаты стресс-теста. У Джо возникает вопрос относительно результатов исследования, которые не показаны на ключевых изображениях в отчёте, поэтому доктор Даун использует локальную информационную систему поликлиники и делает запрос к системе PACS на ресурс <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a>, проходит по ссылкам для открытия изображений из этого исследования. Джо соглашается на процедуру катетеризации полостей сердца, и доктор Даун отправляет направление в отделение катетеризации больницы при Университете Джайномэс и указывает системе PACS дать совместный доступ к результатам эхографии через городскую систему обмена медицинской информацией.
<!-- Dr. Down meets again with Joe, and they review the results of the stress test.  Joe has a question about 
the findings that the key images in the report do not show, so Dr. Down uses the Local MultiClinic EMR 
to query the PACS for the full <a href="imagingstudy.html">ImagingStudy</a> resource, and uses the references there to open an image 
display for the full study.  Joe agrees to proceed to catheterization, and Dr. Down sends a referral to 
the Ginormous University Hospital cath department, and triggers the PACS to share the echo study 
through the Metropolitan Health Information Exchange.   -->
</p>
<p>
Система PACS создаёт манифест исследования в виде ресурса <a href="imagingmanifest.html">ImagingManifest</a>, в который входят все изображения, кроме предварительных измерений специалиста по ультразвуковой эхографии (которые в соответствии с политикой безопасности не доступны вне поликлиники). Этот манифест публикуется в городском реестре обмена медицинской информацией. В соответствии с <a href="http://www.ihe.net">IHE XDS-I</a>, эти изображения непосредственно не публикуются в этой системе обмена медицинской информацией, а становятся доступны по запросу к системе PACS.
<!-- The PACS creates a manifest of the study as an <a href="imagingmanifest.html">ImagingManifest</a> 
resource, which includes all the 
images but excludes the sonographer’s preliminary measurements (which as a matter of policy are 
not shared outside the Local MultiClinic). The manifest is published to the Metro HIE. (In 
accordance with <a href="http://www.ihe.net">IHE XDS-I</a>, the images themselves are not directly 
published to the HIE, but available for on-demand retrieval from the PACS.) -->
</p>
<p>
В больнице Джайномэс докутор Кора Пламмер получает направление на катетеризацию и ищет то исследование в городской системе обмена медицинской информацией. Она извлекает манифест исследования <a href="imagingmanifest.html">ImagingManifest</a> и использует его для доступа к расшаренным изображениям для подготовки к процедуре катетеризации.
<!-- At Ginormous Hospital, Dr. Cora Plummer receives the cath referral, and looks up the study in the 
Metro HIE registry.  She retrieves the study manifest <a href="imagingmanifest.html">ImagingManifest</a>, 
and uses it to access the shared images, which she uses to prepare for the cath procedure. -->
</p>


<!-- old use-case replaced August 2015, CP #7679
<p>
Следующая раскадровка иллюстрирует основной сценарий использования для этого ресурса:
The following storyboard illustrates the primary use case for 
this resource:
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
Онколог Карен принимает пациентов в своей клинике, и хотела бы подготовиться к пациентам, которых она будет принимать сегодня. Ее первый сегодняшний пациент, Алекс, уже прибыл. Она запускает свою систему электронных медицинских записей и ищет Алекса, делая запрос по пациентам и используя его фамилию. СЭМЗ делает FHIR-запрос к ресурсу Patient, чтобы предоставить основную демографическую информацию для отрисовки титульной страницы. СЭМЗ делает последующий FHIR-запрос к ресурсу Condition и сообщает, что у Алекса подозревается рак простаты. Получив эту информацию, Карен решает проверить два следующих теста - результаты лабораторного теста Prostate-Specific Antigen (PSA) и КТ, выполненного с местном диагностическом центре. Первое, FHIR-запрос делается к ресурсу Observation для запроса последнего значения PSA (СЭМЗ также запрашивает предыдущие значения PSA для проверки тенденции). Для КТ-осмотра СЭМЗ запрашивает ресурс ImagingStudy, чтобы получить список доступных изображений с другими существенными ограничениями (такими как модальность, участок тела и т. п.). Этот запрос возвращает доступные исследования, а также значимые метаданные о каждом исследовании, его серию и изображения. Эта информация поможет Карен выбрать, какое исследование она захочет посмотреть. Используя предоставленные WADO-RS-ссылки, артефакты. которые захочет посмотреть Карен, можно загружить и просмотреть с помощью программного обеспечения, поддерживающего просмотр DICOM.
An oncologist, Karen, is seeing patients in her clinic, and would like
background on the patients she is seeing today. Her first patient of the
day, Alex. has arrived. She launches her Electronic Medical Record (EMR)
software, and makes a Patient query on Alex using his last name. The EMR
software makes a FHIR query on the Patient resource, to provide background
demographic information for cover page rendering. The EMR software makes a
subsequent FHIR query on the Condition resource, and reports that Alex is
suspected to have prostate cancer. With this information, Karen decides to
check for two further tests - the results of a Prostate-Specific Antigen
(PSA) laboratory test, and of a CT exam performed at the local diagnostic
facility. First, a FHIR query is made against the Observation resource to
query for the most recent value of PSA (the EMR also queries previous 
values of PSA for trending). For the CT exam, the EMR software queries on
the ImagingStudy resource to retrieve a list of available images with other 
relevant constraints (such as modality, body region etc.). This returns 
back the studies available, with relevant meta-data about each study,
its series and images. This information will help Karen to select which 
study would like to review. Using the WADO-RS references provided, the 
artifacts Karen would like to review can be downloaded and viewed using 
capable DICOM viewing software.
</p>
</blockquote>
-->
</div>
