<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Область применения и использование<!-- Scope and Usage --></h2>
<p>
<!-- Describes some of the situations/use cases intended to be managed with the resource. May include a child div for "Storyboards" and "Related Specifications". The purpose of this section is to help implementers understand why the resource is needed and how it might be used. -->
    <p>
        <b>These resources have not yet undergone proper review by PC, CQI, CDS, and OO. At this time, 
        they are to be considered only as draft resource proposals for potential submission.</b>
    </p>
    
    <p>
	<i>Procedure Request</i> - это запись о запросе на выполнение процедуры. Может использоваться для представления процедуры, которая запланирована, предложена или заказана.
        <!-- A <i>Procedure Request</i> is a record of a request for a procedure to be performed. 
        It can be used to represent a procedure that is planned, that is proposed, or that is ordered. -->
    </p>
    <p>
	<i>Procedure Request</i> может представлять заказ, введенный специалистом (practitioner) в CPOE-систему, а также предложение, сделанное клинической системой поддержки принятия решений (CDSS) на основе медицинской записи пациента и контекста оказания помощи. Запланированные процедуры также могут быть представлены с помощью этого ресурса (хотя этот случай использования все еще обсуждается и требует  проверки рабочими группами Patient Care и Orders and Observation).
        <!-- The procedure request may represent an order that is entered by a practitioner in a CPOE 
        system as well as a proposal made by a clinical decision support system (CDSS) based 
        on a patient's clinical record and context of care. Planned procedures may also be 
        represented by this resource (though this use case is still being discussed and will 
        need to be validated by Patient Care and Orders and Observation). -->
    </p>
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Границы и связи</h2>
<p>
    <b>Примечание для рецензентов<!-- Notes to reviewers -->:</b>

    <p>
        <i>Пожалуйста, обратите внимание, что конкретные границы между ресурсами Diagnostic Order и Procedure Request должны быть определены рабочей группой Patient Care.<!-- Please note that the boundaries between a Diagnostic Order and a Procedure Request will need to be concretely
        defined by Patient Care. --></i>
    </p>
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Предпосылки и контекст</h2>
<p>
Понятие запроса на процедуру (procedure request) имеет ключевое значение для клинической системы поддержки принятия решений, которая может рекомендовать процедуры на основе ряда критериев оценки пациента и другой клинической информации.
<!-- The notion of a procedure request is of key importance to clinical decision support system which may recommend 
procedures based on a number of criteria evaluated on patient and other clinical information. -->
</p>
</div>

</div>
