<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div>
<h2>Область применения и использование</h2>
<p>
Выполнение клинической оценки является фундаментальной частью рабочего процесса клинициста, выполняемой многократно в течение дня.
Несмотря на это - или, возможно, как раз поэтому - имеется широкий разброс в том, как записываются эти клинические оценки.
Некоторые клинические оценки заключаются просто в добавлении наблюдения в виде отдельного текстового комментария к документам пациента (например "Прогресс удовлетворительный,
продолжить лечение"), в то время как другие связаны с тщательным, детальным ведением учета собираемых показателей, рассуждений, ведущих к дифференциальной диагностике, и действий, предпринятых во время или запланированных в результате клинической оценки, и существует весь спектр вариаций между ними. Данный ресурс предназначен для покрытия всех вариантов использования.
<!-- Performing a clinical assessment is a fundamental part of a clinician's workflow, performed repeatedly throughout the day. 
In spite of this - or perhaps, because of it - there is wide variance in how clinical impressions are recorded. 
Some clinical assessments simply result in an impression recorded as a single text note in the patient 'record' (e.g. "Progress satisfactory, 
continue with treatment"), while others are associated with careful, detailed record keeping of the 
evidence gathered, the reasoning leading to a differential diagnosis, and the actions taken during or planned
as a result of the clinical assessment, and there is a continuum between these. This resource is intended to be 
used to cover all these use cases. -->
</p>
<p>
Оценивание тесно связано с процессом лечения. Оно может иметь место в контексте плана мероприятий по уходу и часто заключается в новом (или пересмотренном) плане ухода. Обычно клиническая оценка выполняется в рамках продолжающегося процесса ухода, и состояние пациента оценивается повторно неоднократно. Поэтому ресурс clinical impression может ссылаться как на планы по уходу (предшествующие и последующие), так и на предыдущую клиническую оценку, из которой следует данная. 
<!-- The assessment is intimately linked to the process of care. It may occur in the context of a care plan,
and it very often results in a new (or revised) care plan. Normally. clinical assessments are part of an 
ongoing process of care, and the patient will be re-assessed repeatedly. For this reason, the clinical
impression can explicit reference both care plans (preceeding and resulting) and reference a previous
impression that this impression follows on from. -->
</p>
<p>
В отличие от многих других ресурсов у обмена записями клинических оценок имеется небольшой прототип. По этой причине данный ресурс должен рассматриваться как особо склонный к постоянным правкам. Рабочая группа Patient Care хотела бы обратить особое внимание рецензентов и исполнителей на следующие вопросы с точки зрения масштаба и использования:
<!-- Unlike many other resources, there is little prior art with regard to exchanging records of 
clinical assessments. For this reason, this resource should be regarded as particularly 
prone to ongoing revision. In terms of scope and usage, the Patient Care workgroup wishes to
draw the attention of reviewers and implementers to the following issues:  -->
<a name="dstu"> </a>
</p>
<ul>
 <li>When is an existing clinical impression revised, rather than a new one created (that references the existing one)? How does that affect the status? what's the interplay between the status of the diagnosis and the status of the impression? (e.g. for a 'provisional' impression, which bit is provisional?)</li>
 <li>This structure doesn't differentiate between a working and a final diagnosis. Given an answer to the previous question, should it?</li>
 <li>Further clarify around the relationship between care plan and impression is needed. Both answers to the previous questions and ongoing discussions around revisions to the care plan will influence the design of clinical impression</li>
 <li>Should prognosis be represented, and if so, how much structure should it have?</li>
 <li>Should an impression reference other impressions that are related? (how related?)</li>
 <li>Investigations - the specification needs a good value set for the code for the group, and will be considering the name "investigations" further</li>
<!--  <li>When is an existing clinical impression revised, rather than a new one created (that references the existing one)? How does that affect the status? what's the interplay between the status of the diagnosis and the status of the impression? (e.g. for a 'provisional' impression, which bit is provisional?)</li>
 <li>This structure doesn't differentiate between a working and a final diagnosis. Given an answer to the previous question, should it?</li>
 <li>Further clarify around the relationship between care plan and impression is needed. Both answers to the previous questions and ongoing discussions around revisions to the care plan will influence the design of clinical impression</li>
 <li>Should prognosis be represented, and if so, how much structure should it have?</li>
 <li>Should an impression reference other impressions that are related? (how related?)</li>
 <li>Investigations - the specification needs a good value set for the code for the group, and will be considering the name "investigations" further</li> -->
</ul> 
</div>

<div>
<h2>Границы и связи</h2>
<p>
Есть другое связанное клиническое понятие, которое часто называют "оценкой" - инструменты оценки, например шкала Апгар (также известные как шкалы оценки).
Это совсем не то, что следует записывать в ресурс ClinicalImpression; инструменты оценки, такие как шкала Апгар, описывают с помощью ресурса <a href="observation.html">Observations</a>, а ресурс <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaires</a> можно при этом использовать как вспомогательное средство для этого. Ресурсы ClinicalImpression могут ссылаться на инструменты оценивания в качестве одного из исследований, которые были выполнены в процессе оценивания.
<!-- There is another related clinical concept often called an "assessment": assessment Tools such as Apgar (also known as "Assessment Scales").
This is not what the ClinicalImpression resource is about; assessment tools such as Apgar are represented as 
<a href="observation.html">Observations</a>, and <a href="questionnaire.html">Questionnaires</a> may be used to help 
generate these. Clinical Impressions may refer to these assessment tools as one of the investigations that was performed
during the assessment process. -->
</p>
</div>

<div>
<h2>Предпосылки и контекст</h2>
<p>
Важные исходные данные для понимания этого ресурса можно найти на <a href="http://wiki.hl7.org/index.php?title=Clinical_Assessment">страницах wiki-раздела FHIR</a>. В частности, раскадровка планирования дизайна ресурса, а также основа для всех созданных примеров.
<!-- An important background to understanding this resource is <a href="http://wiki.hl7.org/index.php?title=Clinical_Assessment">the FHIR wiki page for clinical assessment</a>. In particular,
the storyboards there drove the design of the resource, and will be the basis for all examples created. -->
</p>
</div>

</div>
